That's what they say in the court.
I'm heading for Europe, I'm getting in the
mood.
Why knock on your door?
They say knock on your door.
You walk through the door?
No.
They also say if you're really looking at
something, be careful when you're
scrutinizing it.
They say you're screwing it.
Screwing it? Yes.
They'll get a few short marks scrutinizing
it.
Do you ever think it's really nice?
I don't think it's nice.
No, they can't see me how she goes that
way.
They've got red tools.
They've come around and showed me their
chest.
They're black, they're all the other way
around.
Who?
Really?
Huh?
Liberty is only blacks, mostly blacks.
Really?
We have work around in the hotels, living
there.
Stores are almost gone.
Pop, remember when you used to drive up
and we'd stop at the Red Apple Rest?
I've seen this movie in 10 years.
Remember when we used to drive up and stop
at the Red Apple Rest?
Then they made the thruway go.
It'll make me feel better.
I think I look better 10 years from now.
That used to be a great ride, four hours.
And good times, four hours.
There was always the Slotsville traffic
jam.
Or Slotsburg.
Lapsido Park.
All those lovely towns.
Middletown.
Goshen.
That's the traffic Goshen.
Is that they're doing a movie again?
Are they doing another movie?
Why do those guys get lost?
We're gonna get their movie on our video.
Oh, that's fast.
I think we should start.
If I know any more anecdotes, I would've
watched them.
Gene: 86 years ago when grandpa's father
decided he's gonna have, at 75, he's
gonna have another child.
Gene: So nine months later, guess who came
out?
Gene: Now you tell us the story. What
happened from then on?
I don't think it was an accident.
No, I'm sure it was an accident.
Is that microphone loud enough to pick up?
Don't you realize he had another job?
Yeah.
Abe: She died when she was 56 years old.
Abe: He died when he was 91 or 92.
Mom said he was 96.
I remember she said no. She always
exaggerated.
She always exaggerated.
Because I remember computing his birthday
to 1832.
Frances (Fran): She always had a nice
thing to say about him. She always had a
nice thing to say about your father.
Well, he kept, he was an old man.
Yeah, he kept himself clean.
Kept himself very clean.
[Check audio] Abe: He had to be polished
and stay by the bath.
Yeah.
Was he German?
Huh?
German.
Abe: He wasn't German. He was Jewish.
What country was he born in?
He was born in Poland.
What town?
Krasnobród.
How many brothers and sisters did he have?
He had three brothers.
I had two brothers besides him.
Abe: He had two brothers beside him. And
they disappeared. When his brother had to
go in the Russian army, so he escaped. He
didn’t want to go.
Abe: And the other brother also left his
wife with two children.
Abe: He also disappeared in thin air.
Abe: Never knew where he disappeared.
Abe: And so the Russian came to look for
my father's brother.
[Check audio] Abe: [He?] was six years old
at that time.
Abe: That took him, that took him, while
he was six years, that took him in the
army.
He was drafted about that age.
[Check audio] Abe: They called them
“Cantonista.” It was in the millions of
children.
Yeah, sure they had.
Abe: They called them “Cantonista.”
What did they call them?
Abe: “Cantonista.” That was the name of
them.
[Check audio] [Like cadets, probably?]
Abe: I remember a landsman of mine in my
town was 25 years in the army.
Abe: They took him off when he was a
child, about six or eight years.
Abe: When he came back, his name was Leib
Zellner.
Abe: Zellner is a soldier.
Oh, so that was his name.
Abe: So that's how they named him, Leib
Zellner.
Abe: My mother was his third wife.
[Check audio] [Question about children
from his earlier wives; wording unclear.]
Abe: He had two children with his second
wife, but they died.
And the first none?
Abe: The first he didn't have.
Abe: When he married my mother, she gave
birth to nine children.
Nine children, huh?
Yeah.
Are you sure they were all his?
Well, if you looked at them, they looked
so much alike.
Whatever it was, they had the same father.
Abe: My mother was very religious.
Abe: She was a very religious woman.
Abe: Oh, yeah.
Abe: In that time in Europe, they didn't
know monkey business.
Abe: They didn't know monkey business.
That's what you said.
I'm not so sure about that, Pop. I think
monkey business is gone.
Nobody's mother ever knew.
Are these things you really should ask?
Not a video camera.
You expect an honest answer?
[Check audio] Sylvia: It was the German
doctor that helped [unclear pronoun].
Abe: It was a Russian. [Other conversation
overlaps.]
Abe: He had to go around to check if
somebody in the house had typhus, to put
out
a sign for nobody to go in.
Oh, it was typhus?
Abe: At that time my mother was very sick.
She had asthma. She swelled up. He came
in, he examined her. He prescribed two
medicines, and right away she got healthy.
Abe: And after two years or three years,
the war finished.
Abe: He went back home because after the
war they sent all the prisoners of war
home.
Abe: And she got again sick and we threw
away the prescription.
Abe: And the other doctors didn't know.
Abe: So that's how she died.
Abe: She was about 19, 20 weeks in bed. I
came home that time, ten o’clock at
night from work. And then I came in and
she died.
You saw her dying?
Yes.
Frances (Fran): How did Mama's father die?
Frances (Fran): He died when she was very
young, too.
She was an orphan.
[Check audio] ...SARS Pallet, or some
other unit.
[Check audio] That's Mammoth's Pallet.
[Check audio] Yeah, that's Mammoth's
Pallet.
So he tried rushing back into Poland, and
he swam a lake.
And then he got pneumonia?
He got TB.
Oh, he got TB from the lake.
He got TB and...
[Check audio] Pneumonia [unclear].
[Check audio] [Unclear overlapping
discussion of illness and treatment.]
[Check audio] It was TB [remainder
unclear].
Mama always said it was TB that he got.
Yeah, that's what he said.
[Check audio] [Unclear opening.] That’s
why Mom was always afraid of TB herself.
Well, TB was rampant in our family.
That's right, I remember that.
Mama had TB, but she healed up.
How long?
[Check audio] [Her lungs were damaged?]
[Check audio] She used to go around all
over.
And her mother died of what?
What? Her mother died what?
Mama's mother? I don't know.
She said it was brain fever.
It was a stroke.
She said it was brain fever and she was
sick for a while.
Maybe it was a stroke, maybe it was the
same.
I don't know.
Sylvia: When I was sick with encephalitis,
I was 28, and that was the age that
mom's mother was when she died.
Sylvia: And she said it sounded, you know,
her...
[Check audio] Well, it's probably her
actual name.
[Check audio] [No reliable transcription
for this interval; check the recording.]
Oh, that's right, she married again, Mom's
mother.
At least that was Mom's view of the world.
That was Mom's view of the world, yes.
My mother's mother remarried.
It wasn't good for the stepchildren, you
know.
Well, she was 17, right?
[Check audio] No, this is my mother who
was 17 when she married me.
Her mother?
My mother was about 26. In her 20s, her
husband died, and then she was forced to
marry an old man.
[Check audio] She had two little children.
She was only about 28 years old.
So she was forced to marry this old man,
my mother used to say.
This old man.
She think that...
Sylvia: Tortured her to death.
Frances (Fran): Well, not
tortured—mitchered. Mitchered has more of
an annoyance,
pestered her.
She thought that maybe was the...
History is being made here.
Yeah, let's get it to the answer.
This is it.
Just to tell us about how you carried this
water at night.
First World War.
to carry things from one town to another.
Abe: When the war broke out, they took my
brother to the army. He was in the
reserve. He was such a nice-looking man.
[Check audio] When he came home from the
army, he was in the south,
[Check audio] you know, Jewish people.
Abe: He came home, he was so nice-looking,
the girls were crazy about him. When he
went to the army, he left a girl. She was
older. She had a red scar on her face.
Abe: But it looks like he was in love with
her. He was in the army. He had other
Jewish friends.
Abe: The Jewish girls used to go out and
send us pictures with him.
Abe: And he came home. He started again to
go with this girl. So people came over
to my mother: how come you let such a
nice-looking man get married to Yitta?
Abe: Her name was Yitta. My mother said,
“I wouldn’t sleep with her, but he likes
her.”
Frances (Fran): She doesn’t have to sleep
with her. The son has to sleep with her.
She’s not going to interfere.
Abe: She arranged a nice wedding. The
tailor used to come in our house to make
everybody suits.
Abe: And then two years later the war
broke out.
Abe: They had two children, a boy and a
girl. The boy died. He got chickenpox or
measles.
Abe: And he was staying right near the
Austrian border.
Abe: Then the Austrians tried to go across
the border.
Abe: That's when the army...
Abe: And he was the first to get killed.
He was your oldest brother?
He's not... the second one.
What's his name?
Abe: His name was Yisroel. [The name is
repeated in overlapping speech.]
What about the cousin that you were so
close to?
That was close to you?
Was it that close, as we say?
Which cousin?
Abe: And then they notified the rabbi in
our town.
Abe: Mama didn't believe.
Abe: And then another brother went to the
army.
Abe: He was captured by the Germans. He
used to send us money from there. He was a
tailor. He used to make suits for them,
dresses. He earned money, he used to send
us money.
[Check audio] Abe: And in the Second World
War, he got killed [unclear words].
He also got killed?
Abe: He and his wife and five children.
Oh, German World War II. That's when the
Germans went into Poland.
Yeah.
This is World War II?
[Check audio] Abe: He escaped to Russia.
In Ukraine, he settled in a town. And he
didn’t have a chance. When the Germans
approached, they chased him in a mine
shaft. And they let in water and drowned
the whole town.
The Germans or the Ukrainians?
The Germans.
The World War I?
The World War II.
He survived one.
He got his two.
[Check audio] Abe: [Unclear opening about
Yitta.] They were in a different town
and they got saved. Her daughter, Hansha
was her name. You saw Hansha and you saw
[Yitzak]. My older brother’s son, and
they’re married.
Abe: So he was also... he was such a
healthy man.
Abe: The Germans caught him.
Abe: And a soldier took him someplace
to...
Abe: To the train to send him into Germany
for work, or to kill him.
So they passed by...
[Check audio] It's what, what, how do you
call it, a well.
A well.
[Check audio] Abe: You know, with the pail
they used to bring up the water. He
said he’s thirsty, so the German let him
drink the water. Then the German went
over to drink… [Abe gestures the action,
according to Nancy.]
And threw him in the well?
Abe: No, he threw the German in the well.
When was this?
When he was being captured, when he was
being shipped to...
Sylvia: Which brother was this, pop?
Abe: That was Yitzak, my brother’s son.
[Check audio] Oh, your brother's son, the
nephew.
[Check audio] Oh.
Abe: Then they were both in Israel. He
died.
I was looking for you. I was waiting for
you.
You said 1 o'clock?
We thought you would come here first.
We thought you'd come here first to
change.
We thought you'd come and get Grandpa.
[Check audio] [Unclear side conversation.]
Where's Ethel right here?
I'm giving her to you.
That's all right.
And now we can leave.
So, Grandpa was...
What year was that? Was that World War II?
[Check audio] [World War II; overlapping
response unclear.]
Abe: But in the First World War, I was at
that time, the Russians were at that
time.
[Check audio] Abe: Russia had occupied
[unclear]—Russian Poland.
[Check audio] Abe: And when the Germans
made successes on the front, they started
to push toward [our town?].
[Check audio] Abe: So a group of engineers
came to our town to dig trenches [to
fight the Germans?].
Abe: So I was at that time 14 years old.
Abe: They took out everybody on a Saturday
to take to work, to dig trenches.
Abe: So a rabbi came out and said,
Abe: He said, it’s Sabbath, we’re not
allowed to work.
Abe: Let us tomorrow in the morning,
Abe: Everybody’s going to come out and dig
trenches.
Abe: The storekeepers, they couldn’t; they
had to attend to business.
[Check audio] Abe: But children—me and my
[brother’s son?],
[Check audio] Abe: [He was my age?] We
used to go, boys. And they used to pay us
a
ruble a day.
Abe: We worked a whole week, and on Sunday
was paid.
Abe: Just to stay with Polish people.
Sometimes the Pollock beat us up.
Abe: But we were staying in the line for
later for the pay.
Frances (Fran): They used to beat you up?
Abe: Yeah.
Sylvia: Why?
Abe: Why?
Abe: Why? Why?
[Possibly Sylvia and Fran]: Because they
were Jewish!
Abe: Because... right
Abe: After a couple weeks they gave an
order the whole town has to leave.
Abe: So we stopped in the woods.
Abe: There was no place where to go.
[Check audio] Abe: We used to make fires
and [cook?].
Abe: Then came another order.
Abe: We cannot stay in the woods.
Abe: So we escaped.
Abe: My mother and my brother, all the
brothers,
[Check audio] Abe: [Unclear wording about
Poles and wagons.] And we went to
Zamość, a big town.
Abe: Over there we had a cousin.
Abe: He stayed with them.
Abe: While we escaped, they burned up the
whole town.
Abe: The Russians, before they left, they
burned the town.
Abe: So after we stayed a couple weeks, it
was very crowded.
Abe: We had only one room.
Abe: We came back to our town.
Abe: We couldn't go back because it was
burned up, so we stopped in a village.
Abe: And we also stayed outside.
Abe: I used to make a little hill.
[Check audio] Abe: I used to dig in. It
was sandy ground. I used to go and pick up
[wood?] and make a fire on top.
[Check audio] I used to cook. Once I was
put my foot in there and my brother put
his in the whole sand.
[Check audio] I sent, I sent, follow my
foot.
What happened?
The whole fire?
[Check audio] The [sand], the hot [sand],
[fell on?] my foot.
And then...
What did they do when they made the fire?
They didn't know what to do so they looked
for...
[Check audio] Abe: We had a Jewish man, a
[storekeeper?], who was a rich man.
[Check audio] Abe: He was very good
natured, but he didn't have no room for us
[to
live in?].
Abe: But at night, he used to go up on the
attic and let us sleep at night on the
attic.
Abe: So everybody who passed by came up
there to sleep in the attic.
Abe: How big was the attic?
Abe: The attic was big and it was hay.
Abe: And the attic, and it started to get
dirty with lice, you know.
Abe: And we, everybody got a sickness.
Abe: They got rashes.
So you got sick from the lice. They
transmitted something.
Abe: We got rashes.
You were 15?
Abe: I was about 15 years old.
And who was, who were you living with
then?
Who was everybody in your family?
Everybody in the family.
He and all those brothers looked around
and they found the house.
The Russians escaped. They were afraid for
the Austrians, so they left the house.
So his brother rent us the house and we
opened up like a grocery.
Abe: We had kerosene to sell, and whiskey
and salt and sugar.
Abe: At night my mother and my brother
used to go around by the peasants and buy
butter and eggs.
Abe: And every morning, three o'clock in
the morning, everybody would have a
package.
[Check audio] Abe: We went from that
village to Zamość, about three miles [unit
uncertain]. We came in at that time, eight
o’clock in the morning, and we sold it.
[Check audio] We sold it. They knew where
I was going to go, so we sold it.
Abe: On the way back we bought sugar and
kerosene; everybody carried it back.
Abe: And then next to our house, Austrian
gendarmes moved in. Police, but military
police.
[Check audio] Because at that time, in
wartime, it was [unclear].
Abe: They took a Polish woman as a maid.
Abe: She came into my mother to borrow a
pot.
Abe: My mother was religious: she’ll
borrow a pot, she’ll make a traif.
Abe: So she refused.
[Check audio] Abe: [Unclear words.] She
told the sergeant [the family had taken
wood; Nancy’s interpretation].
Abe: So on a Friday night he came in and
he started to beat my brother.
[Check audio] My mother used to say
[unclear].
What was that?
[Check audio] He started beating [him],
because his mother wouldn’t give the pot
to this woman.
She told a story about him.
And the soldiers came.
[Check audio] The old woman lay in bed and
don't answer nothing.
Abe: We were afraid to stay there.
[Check audio] Abe: Once my father went to
a town and he bought whiskey, five
gallons of whiskey.
[Check audio] Abe: We were at the bar of
the house.
[Check audio] Abe: A young man came over,
you there, what are you carrying?
Abe: He said, “Kerosene.”
[Check audio] Abe: So he opened up and he
smelled the sauce whiskey.
[Check audio] Abe: He took his gun, banged
and he dropped it.
[Check audio] Abe: So we saw we cannot
stay there no more.
Abe: So we moved in in another village.
Abe: The other village we moved in was
German; they lived there for years in
Poland.
Abe: So they used to come in.
Abe: The ruble was more valuable than the
Austrian mark, crown.
Abe: So they used to come in.
Abe: My mother used to ask them, but what
kind of money are you going to buy?
Abe: They said the ruble.
Abe: Then they had the fact that the
merchandise, they took out Austrian
crowns.
Abe: So I lost money.
Abe: So we had to move away.
Abe: My brother moved to Tomaszów. My
sister-in-law had parents there.
So they moved in, find an apartment.
[Check audio] Abe: My brother used to
carry flour and salt from one store to
another. They called them carriers,
[tragers?].
Abe: And we came back in town. The town
was burned up.
Abe: So a woman, which we know, we were
friends, took us in.
Abe: It was my sister-in-law’s sister. She
gave us the courtesy to take us in when
my mother was sick.
[Check audio] And they used to, and it was
small children, they used to go in the
market to buy,
[Check audio] and the children went
around, and my children would ask.
Abe: My mother couldn’t stay. And money we
didn’t have.
Abe: So I went over in a town, in a town
we had relatives.
Abe: But they were also poor, so one boy
was my age, he was a year younger.
Abe: He took me to my mother's relatives
in a small village.
Abe: There were tailors there. They used
to work for the peasantry.
Abe: So we went there and they gave me, at
that time, a nice couple of money too.
Abe: I came back in Tomaszów. It was a big
snow falling, and I couldn’t go back to
Krasnobród.
Abe: So somebody, I found out somebody
with a sled, with a horse, he gave me, he
took me there.
Abe: He took me there. I was the only one
to take care of them. My father was
sick.
Frances: Where was Victor all this time?
Abe: Victor was in America.
Family member: When did he come? Abe: He
went in 1913.
Abe: We were six brothers and one sister.
And I was the youngest.
[Check audio] Did your father have other
children now?
[Check audio] Six from your mother?
[Check audio] They used to leave them to
go.
[Check audio] Right away, they went in the
back wagon.
[Check audio] The boys would move.
Abe: In Tomaszów, we had a far distant
cousin, mother’s cousin.
[Check audio] Excuse me.
Abe: Mama’s distant relative.
[Check audio] Not the one from Brooklyn.
Abe: So, the rich man, he used to have a
concession for tobacco, whiskey, you
know,
Abe: and he would go to them and maybe
they would help.
[Check audio] Abe: [Unclear conversation
with the woman; Nancy understands Abe to
be asking for help because his mother was
sick.]
Abe: So she gave me half a bread,
potatoes. But money, I don’t think she
gave me.
You had to talk louder.
I had to talk.
Louder, Pop.
He used to go around.
Why don't you draw the chairs up?
Abe: He used to go around to the owners
and stores.
[Check audio] Abe: I had to go clean the
streets and dig the site.
[Check audio] Abe: So I didn't have no
time to go.
[Check audio] Abe: So they used to give me
a ruble.
[Check audio] That's how I used to go.
That's how I used to go.
Where was I born? I can't remember.
[Check audio] Where was I born? Tomaszów?
You were born in Tomaszów.
[Check audio] Grandma was from Tomaszów,
right?
[Check audio] Grandma was from Tomaszów
and you were from Krasnobród.
[Check audio] And so you moved to
Tomaszów. In the war time, we moved to
Tomaszów.
[Check audio] Tomaszów was wiped off the
map. No, it's still on the map.
[Check audio] It's a different Tomaszów.
[Check audio] There's no Tomaszów
anywhere.
[Check audio] There is a Tomaszów on the
map.
[Check audio] Zamość?
[Check audio] What was Zamość?
[Check audio] There was two Zamość.
It was an old city.
It's a city that what's his name? Michner
writes about.
[Check audio] So it's Zamość.
They were the old city and the new city
together.
They were right together?
Yeah, you could have walked from one to
the other.
[Check audio] Where was Zamość? Was that
near Krasnobród?
[Check audio] That's between Krasnobród
and Tomaszów.
All kinds of small towns.
What's the story, Grandpa, when you were
arrested for your cousin?
How did that happen? What's the story?
[Check audio] Abe: This happened before,
when I got my ticket to go to America
from [Victor?].
Abe: So I made a passport.
Make it a little louder, Pa.
Abe: I had to make a passport.
[Check audio] Abe: I had to go to the
police department [unclear words].
Abe: And then I had to go to the draft
board.
[Check audio] Abe: That was in different
[towns?].
Abe: Because I was born in Krasnobród, I
had to go to Zamość, to the draft board.
Abe: to the draft board. And I got
everything and I made a passport and I
went to
Warsaw to
[Check audio] Abe: They postponed me for a
year. [Unclear words about the visa.]
So I came back.
They postponed it? They said you couldn't
leave yet?
The quota was closed. Oh, that was our
quota.
The United States quota. The quota was...
I couldn't go no more.
[Check audio] Abe: [Unclear words about
the delay.] At that point I got married.
Frances (Fran): So during that time you
got married?
Abe: During that year I got married, yeah.
Abe: I figured maybe I wouldn't be able to
go even after a year.
Frances (Fran): So you might as well get
married.
Abe: Might as well get married.
Abe: So I got married.
Abe: A year later, in 1922, in May, I got
a letter from the consulate that I
should come get the visa.
Abe: So my passport expired. I had to make
a new one.
[Check audio] [Unclear words about the
passport.]
Abe: So I had to go again to the police
and again to the draft board.
Abe: And I came to the draft board.
Abe: I put an application up on the...
so...
[Check audio] Here, it's civil people in
the [draft board?], over there's
soldiers.
Abe: So the... the lieutenant told me,
Abe: come next week.
Abe: I came next week.
Abe: He was busy, he couldn't do it.
[Check audio] [Unclear words.]
Abe: I had to go from one city to another.
Abe: Finally, once I came down, a Jewish
man asked me,
Abe: he says, you've got to get money.
Abe: Tell him you'll give him money, maybe
he'll do it.
Abe: So I went back in and told him,
Abe: if you make it, I'll give you a nice
tip.
Abe: I came back a week later.
Frances (Fran): So they gave it to you.
Abe: I got it.
Abe: Then I got to Warsaw for the visa.
Abe: I came late.
Abe: Until I got my passport in order.
Abe: The visa was out.
Abe: So I came there. They gave me another
three weeks to come for the visa.
Abe: So I came home.
Abe: When I came home I had to go work
because I had to make a living.
Abe: And I was working in a shoemaker.
Abe: I came home on a Thursday night.
Every Thursday was a market.
[Check audio] Abe: All the peasants used
to come with horses and with wagons and
with [cherries?] and all kinds of food.
Abe: That was in the summertime.
Abe: time. And I come home and I sit down
and I eat supper. My oldest brother's
little girl,
Abe: she was about three years old, the
police were looking for Tabak. So they
came to
Abe: my brother. So she heard they were
looking for me. So she brought him in. She
didn't
Abe: She didn't mean anything. She didn't
know.
Abe: A policeman comes in, says,
Abe: Abram Tabak? Yes.
[Check audio] Abe: Obiruse.
[Check audio] Abe: Polish Obiruse. Get
dressed.
Abe: I was just sitting and eating supper.
Abe: I felt everything is in order. I'm
not afraid.
Abe: And I come.
Abe: While I was going past by the town,
everybody was looking.
Abe: Everybody asked me, what's the
matter? What did I arrest you?
[Check audio] Abe: I said nothing. I
passed by shoemaker, I used to work with
him.
Abe: He said, if anything I could help. I
said no.
Abe: I come into the police station, the
sergeant came over to me.
Abe: You want to go to America, you have
to go in the army. Arrest him.
[Check audio] Abe: It was on a Thursday
night. I was sitting Thursday night and
Friday all day; Saturday morning…
Abe: A policeman on a horse, and I was
walking.
Abe: They took me to the one...
Talk a little louder.
Abe: He was on a horse and I was walking.
Abe: They brought me into a village.
Abe: I came to the village and they
brought me into the police.
[Check audio] They didn't... What is that
then? A young boy...
He didn't look Jewish either.
Abe: I looked much younger also than...
Abe: He said, here the people from your
town have an orchard, pears and apples.
It was very friendly. I used to live with
them.
Abe: I go over and they give me pears and
apples. They didn’t have no jail to put
me in.
Abe: So they arranged with another Pollock
to take me to another town.
[Check audio] Abe: So they took me into a
small town, [name unclear].
Abe: They brought me in Friday nights.
[Check audio] Abe: And I didn’t know how
[Mama’s relatives?—unclear].
Abe: I don't know how they found out.
Abe: They came up to the jail and they
brought me something to eat.
Abe: They gave the watchman in jail.
Abe: He wanted to put me by the door, in
straw.
Abe: So they paid him and they put me in
this bed.
Abe: He was sleeping by the door. I
shouldn't escape.
Abe: They had a passport.
Abe: And the next morning they took me in
another town.
Abe: A young boy brought me in jail.
Abe: And somehow a Jewish man came over.
Abe: He said, are you?
Abe: I said, from Krasnobród.
Abe: Oh yeah, I'm also from Krasnobród.
Abe: And he also brought me something to
eat.
Abe: A landsman. He’s a Krasnobród man.
Abe: And the next day they arranged with
him, he should take me to another town.
Frances (Fran): Oh, the soldiers gave up?
Abe: No, no soldiers. All the civilian
people took me.
Abe: Because they gave them the passport.
Abe: And they knew I'm not going to run
away without a passport.
What could I do with her?
Abe: And in Tomaszów, they didn’t know
where I disappeared.
[Check audio] Abe: So Mama came there, my
older brother, and Calman.
Abe: And they were waiting and waiting.
[Check audio] Abe: [They thought for
sure?] that they killed me.
Abe: And Friday, four o'clock, I came in
in the town.
Abe: I was never there.
Abe: And I didn't know nobody.
Abe: I walked around and looked.
[Check audio] A boy, a Polish boy, wanted
to take me. [by a shortcut?] right in
the draft board.
So I told him, maybe I have here somebody.
You hungry, I'm hungry.
You'll eat. Then they'll go. And they
listened to me. They agreed.
And I walk around
Abe: I walked around a tin smith’s stall.
Took a look. A Tomaszów boy was standing
there.
[Check audio] Abe: He says, “I just saw
Telca and your brother,” and he showed me
where she stays. [Overlapping speech
unclear.]
Abe: And they made me something to eat.
They gave that Polish boy to eat.
Abe: and they arranged for that it was a
lawyer.
Abe: He was a Polish citizen. He was a
cripple.
Abe: They gave him ten dollars,
Abe: but I had to pay for the visa,
Abe: I had to give in.
Abe: So he...
Abe: Then they brought me up in the draft
board.
Abe: That lawyer arranged for a
lieutenant.
Abe: He should take over the passport and
let me go and then give me the passport
to the lawyer.
Abe: When they brought me in, that
lieutenant went home already. There was
another
lieutenant.
Abe: He asked me, how old are you?
[Check audio] Abe: I told him [unclear].
Abe: Eighteen years.
Abe: So he asked the soldiers, the riders,
how old does that boy look?
Abe: One says fifteen, one says seventeen.
Abe: Says you go home.
Abe: Go come Monday.
Abe: Because Friday night.
Abe: And I came back.
Abe: The lawyer says, he is going to get
the passport.
Abe: Even if it’s going to cost him his
money.
Abe: And then at night, in the place where
we were staying by Mama’s cousin,
[Check audio] Abe: So tailor comes in
there, says, people, give me $5 and I'll
get
you the passport.
[Check audio] Abe: That lieutenant knew
that tailor.
Abe: And he came to him and he said, I
have a passport that's supposed to go to
America.
Abe: Bring me $5.
Abe: But everybody in the town called him
a liar.
Abe: Not a reliable man. So they said they
don’t need it. And that lawyer, they
didn’t know who had the passport. But he
said, “Don’t worry, even if it’s…”
[Check audio] Abe: “…going to cost me my
own twenty dollars, I’ll get it.”
[Unclear words about Friday/the following
week.]
Rita: Did he have to pay $20?
Abe: I don't know. He didn't.
Frances (Fran): Actually, you had a lot of
nice people that helped you.
It sounds like he asked a lot of people to
help him.
He didn't ask for them.
Yeah, a lot of people. Nice people.
How much did $20 come to this one?
I changed $20 to get a half a million
marks.
[Check audio] Until I came from Russia,
the half a million marks were worth
nothing.
[Check audio] Well, that was inflation
they had in Europe after World War II.
The money didn’t mean nothing.
[Check audio] [Unclear joke comparing the
currency with toilet paper.]
How much did Victor get paid?
But I meant the amount that you paid.
No, but I paid for it.
I made $1.60 a week.
That's here.
But in Poland, what was the $20 worth?
The money that you...
It was a lot.
[Check audio] They used to call it
[noodles?].
Noodles?
Noodles.
Because it was...
They were not allowed to talk about
dollars.
Oh, I see. It was a code word. It was a
code word.
Same word. Dough. Dough, yeah.
Oh, that's why they called it noodles.
Yeah, that's right.
Pasta.
I don't get that dough word.
Any doughs? Any noodles?
Dough, dough, dough.
So noodles was the code word.
On the table, black market.
So they could have heard the word dough,
they called it noodles.
So I paid it. It was $10 for a visa. I had
to give away the lawyer. So I didn't
have no money. So I went to Warsaw. In
Warsaw we had a cousin. I came there. I
went to the HIAS.
The HIAS was a big organization in America
when people came over.
They're still here, the HIAS.
They're still here.
But they're not assigned.
[Check audio] Abe: I sent a telegram to
Victor. [Unclear reply about the money
Victor sent.]
Is that how you got the visa?
I had the visa.
Abe: They sent me money for the visa, but
I was too late for the consulate.
Abe: So I changed that time $20 and I got
a half a million mark.
Abe: I went back to Zamość. It was before
the holidays.
[Check audio] Abe: And after the holidays,
I went [and got my visa].
Frances (Fran): That's when I was
conceived, about that time.
Frances (Fran): I wasn't born until he
came to the United States.
[Check audio] Abe: She was born when I was
in Belgium, in Antwerp.
[Check audio] Abe: I received a letter.
[Check audio] Abe: She was born.
[Check audio] Did your mother know that he
was leaving the United States?
That's why she married him.
[Check audio] [Unclear words about being
on the way to America.]
No, but you know how he got put in jail
and arrested?
She had any idea that he was going through
all this and had plans to really...
No.
She didn't know until he called up from
America?
No, she knew that he was going to go to
the United States,
but she didn't know what happened in
between with the soldiers.
What did she find out?
She went to Warsaw.
Then she found out she went to Warsaw.
[Check audio] So you and Ari left Grandma
thinking that you weren't going to see
her until America.
She didn't know you were going to jail.
[Check audio] I wouldn’t be able to see
her until [unclear].
[Check audio] Yeah.
[Check audio] Fran, you were the man.
[Check audio] What did the problems take
you on?
Frances (Fran): Well, in Connecticut, they
wanted me to get my own papers.
Frances (Fran): So that's when my problems
started,
Frances (Fran): because I don't know
whether they weren't married legally or
what.
Frances (Fran): All the stories were
different.
Frances (Fran): When I had to get my own
papers, the immigration, you know,
investigated.
Frances (Fran): And they said, they've
heard of crazy stories. Most immigrants
had
crazy stories.
Frances (Fran): But this was the craziest.
My mother's name was different.
Frances (Fran): They couldn't find any
record of a marriage.
When I sent the papers, I sent you the age
and mom and everything.
Frances (Fran): was mixed up but because
he was an experienced man and knew that
these things happened with
[Check audio] Frances (Fran): the
immigrants, he allowed, you know, he let
it go
through. But he says I never [saw] such
Frances (Fran): a mess.
What about the rest of the kids?
They were all born in the United States.
That's why there's a big age difference.
Yeah, and then me.
[Check audio] Did she look like an
American?
[Check audio] Do you have any changes?
[Check audio] No changes.
[Check audio] How old were you when you
came to America?
Frances (Fran): I was six years old.
Frances (Fran): A week before I had to go
to school.
Six years.
Frances (Fran): And I didn't have
bilingual classes in those days either,
boys.
Frances (Fran): And the first teacher I
had made fun of me.
Frances (Fran): She hit me over the head
with a ruler.
Remember?
Frances (Fran): remember? And I started to
cry, you know, and my nose was running
like it is now, and
Frances (Fran): I didn't know from
handkerchiefs. I didn't have a
handkerchief. So
she made fun of me
Frances (Fran): for that, too. But then
there was a, I came home crying, and one
of, it wasn't, it wasn't
Frances (Fran): Annie. Not cousin, but she
was related.
[Check audio] [Discussion of the
relationship to Annie; exact words
unclear.]
Frances (Fran): She was very involved in
the parents association, that kind of
thing.
Frances (Fran): She went to school and
complained.
Frances (Fran): The next day I had a
wonderful young Italian teacher who took
me
under her wing.
Frances (Fran): Never saw the other
teacher again. I don't know what ever
happened
to him.
I heard she was fired.
Harry: No, I heard she was fired.
Harry: Because I heard the story from
Sadie, who was Anne's sister.
Oh, really?
She was fired.
The first teacher made fun of me, hit me
over the head with the ruler.
[Check audio] I had her hand on my head.
[Check audio] And then made fun of me
because my nose was running.
[Check audio] I don't know if anyone at
school wanted to teach you that.
[Check audio] Yes, he did say he
remembered.
[Check audio] You know, Mama went down
[unclear].
She went down to buy something and she
forgot the address.
She walked around and she almost went
crazy.
Frances (Fran): That used to happen to me.
Frances (Fran): I'd go to school and you'd
move in between.
Frances (Fran): I once couldn't find a
house.
Not you.
But it happened to me too.
Yeah, I bet it happened.
She went down to buy and she couldn't find
a place to go back.
How long had she been here?
How long had she been here when she
couldn't go back?
[Check audio] She wasn’t [here long?].
Abe: I moved in a house, a new house, like
a basement.
Abe: I had to walk down a couple of
stairs.
Abe: Yeah, I remember that place.
Abe: A new house, a beautiful place at
that time.
Abe: $45 a month rent. I bought new
furniture and everything.
Abe: And for four months the landlord
didn't come for rent.
Abe: So I figure four months is already a
nice couple of dollars.
Abe: And in the front of the house was a
school.
[Check audio] Abe: [Unclear words about
children at the school.]
Too noisy?
Noisy.
So I went and found an apartment for $38 a
month.
Abe: A month concession—two months: a
month you move in and a month you move
out.
Abe: So I hired an expressman.
Abe: He brought me barrels and I packed
them.
Frances (Fran): He was an expert packer.
Abe: While I had already packed them,
Frances (Fran): In five minutes he had
that place packed?
Abe: The landlord came in to them.
Abe: I told him I moved.
Abe: He saw the barrels packed.
Abe: He didn't say a word.
[Check audio] I wanted to see you, you
know I'm not going to pay you.
[Check audio] You know what's wrong.
[Check audio] Oh, it's his fault.
[Check audio] He didn't get me to come.
[Check audio] How did that happen all the
time?
[Check audio] They get concessions.
[Check audio] See, the house, when I was
the one...
Frances (Fran): In order for the landlord
to encourage you to rent their
apartment,
Frances (Fran): because there were lots of
apartments,
Frances (Fran): they would give you the
first month free and the last month free.
The last month.
Frances (Fran): And my mother took
advantage of that.
Frances (Fran): And then I left. She moved
almost every month for a while there.
Six months.
Every year, not every month.
Every year.
[Check audio] She moved at the concession.
We moved away.
[Check audio] But I'm sure it was a
concession.
[Check audio] If they were getting
concessions afterwards, then it's a lot of
money.
[Check audio] Six months, just to be sure.
So one...
Four months, you get four months free a
year.
Frances (Fran): One time, I was watching,
I was watching on Clinton Avenue we
lived.
Frances (Fran): I was watching Rita and
the old house.
Frances (Fran): In the meantime, the
sheriff came and evicted us.
Frances (Fran): Yes, Mama was getting
another apartment, and we were out in the
street.
Frances (Fran): I was crying with her.
Frances (Fran): I didn't know what to do.
No, I remember where he lived.
Because I remember living in two places.
Nobody told us.
Frances (Fran): Oh yes, my apartment.
Please, the furniture was outside.
Frances (Fran): You don't remember that.
The furniture was outside, yes.
By the time, Mama had another apartment
already. We moved.
She didn't expect to have one.
He didn't know. He was at work.
Frances (Fran): By the time, we were out
on the sidewalk, and I was babysitting
her, and she used to cry all the time.
Frances (Fran): Wait, you're out of the
sidewalk?
Frances (Fran): He was working. My mother
got another apartment. I was watching
her. In the meantime, the sheriff came and
evicted us.
Because she didn't pay the rent, I guess.
She didn't pay the rent, yeah. That was
where that Italian woman used to live next
door. Remember?
That sounds so familiar. I must have been
around then. No, you were not.
I must have heard the story.
You must have heard the story.
Frances (Fran): She was such a beautiful
young lady, and the parents would not let
her marry.
Frances (Fran): She never married.
Frances (Fran): So she was comforting me
at that time.
I don't remember.
Well, you were working, but I remember.
[Check audio] But Jim, you came home from
work and you were settled in the
building.
How do you remember those numbers? I
remember the building.
I came home from work and we were already
in the new apartment.
[Check audio] Abe: But, [Clinton Avenue?],
we lived in three houses.
Abe: Sometimes I had dreams.
Abe: I didn't know where to go.
Abe: Sometimes I had a dream, I didn't
know where to go home.
Frances (Fran): I come home from school
and I forgot.
[Check audio] Frances (Fran): My mother
used to say I had a “cotton cup” [phonetic
reading; expression uncertain].
Frances (Fran): I couldn't remember a lot
of things. I still don't.
Frances (Fran): And I forgot that we were
moving.
Frances (Fran): And I went home to the old
house and it wasn't there.
Frances (Fran): I don't remember how they
found me.
Harry: I was lost also for a while once.
Oh yes, you were, yes.
What happened to her?
I remember, yeah, went to the market or
something.
Harry: Like they followed the wrong woman
out of the store or something.
She got lost.
Abe: She went in the market to buy
something and he walked out.
Abe: He walked out, yeah.
Abe: He walked a nice couple blocks and
everybody was running around and everybody
was looking for him.
Abe: And he was saying a man was fixing a
car and he was waiting to watch it.
Abe: That's how you got the motors, huh?
That's how you watched the motors.
How old was Harry? Two and a half?
About four years.
[Check audio] Sylvia: Do you remember the
time you almost [drowned me?]?
You were in the pool?
Yeah.
Sylvia: I was a toddler.
Sylvia: I mean, it was somewhere between
one and two years old, I think.
[Check audio] [I was panicking?] Water
[unclear].
[Check audio] [Over my head?]
Maybe that's why.
I can't remember.
In Pennsylvania.
Pennsylvania.
Well, I had all these fears.
I'm like that.
Well, she communicated.
that fear to me and I did my best to pass
it on to the people.
We believe in sharing truth.
Frances (Fran): But I almost drowned in
Pennsylvania.
I watched you almost drown.
Frances (Fran): And a man came and saved
me.
Where were you?
My uncle Victor used to live in
Pennsylvania,
[Check audio] [Town name unclear],
Pennsylvania.
She didn't know how to swim.
How old was she?
Frances (Fran): I was 12.
And you did that without knowing how to
swim?
Frances (Fran): I was watching her there.
Frances (Fran): It was a little swimming
hole, and it was not deep.
Frances (Fran): But there must have been
a...
Frances (Fran): And we used to have this
swing on a tree.
Frances (Fran): It was very, very...
Frances (Fran): It wasn't very deep.
Frances (Fran): But there must have been a
storm and a hole.
Oh, it got deep.
It got deep.
Frances (Fran): And somehow or other, I
either hurt my hand or something.
Frances (Fran): I let go of the rope, and
I went down.
Frances (Fran): And up, down, and up.
Frances (Fran): up and a man with his
clothes happened to be there and he jumped
in and saved me.
Frances (Fran): And then I kept telling
them, don't tell mama, don't tell mama.
Frances (Fran): And I came home and she
yelled at me.
[Check audio] Frances (Fran): You know,
you're crossing the street, how can you
cross the street?
But that was a lot of fun.
[Check audio] How come Uncle Victor, I
remember, down at these white chickens.
[Check audio] You were a little older than
the chickens. We loved the chickens.
So, what was Uncle Victor doing with a
chicken farm in Pennsylvania?
He didn't have a chicken farm.
So what was he doing? What were the
chickens?
There was a factory.
Oh, I see.
No, Uncle Victor kept chickens. He did.
A few. It wasn't a lot of chickens.
[Check audio] Oh, yeah, that's where my
mama used to get eggs.
[Check audio] [Unclear question about
eggs.]
[Check audio] You know, they're not that
much for the eggs.
[Check audio] We have big morning.
[Check audio] Fresh eggs.
[Check audio] And there was one time on...
Frances (Fran): I was grown up already,
fairly grown up.
Frances (Fran): I was sleeping with you
and I got home a little later and
everybody was sleeping and they
Frances (Fran): didn't hear me knocking on
the door.
Frances (Fran): Immediately I had a vision
that everybody was dead there in the
apartment.
Frances (Fran): I was knocking on the
door, so a neighbor of mine let me go
around
by the fire escape.
Frances (Fran): And then I walked, there
was one, must have been close to 16,
because I had my sweet 16 party there.
Frances (Fran): The only party I ever had,
yeah.
So you weren't six. Why did you get there
all dead?
Frances (Fran): Because my mother was a
very light sleeper. Never happened that
they didn't hear me.
Frances (Fran): I had this vision that
they were all dead there.
Frances (Fran): I said, my whole family's
dead.
Hey, Pap, let's go back a little further.
Where did the name Tabak come from?
How did you know?
Remember, how did the name Tabak come
from?
[Check audio] Didn't you tell me once
about somebody who was [snuff?]?
Abe: Years ago, Jewish people didn't have
second names.
Yeah, I know that.
Abe: So when they start to register second
names,
Abe: A man came in if he was a goldsmith,
they named him goldsmith.
Abe: Whatever he used to do, they would
name him.
[Check audio] If somebody sold [word/name
unclear], they named him [unclear].
[Check audio] [Unclear name or word?]
He was a tailor? He was a tailor?
He used to be a tailor.
Abe: Then my great-grandfather came in.
[Check audio] Abe: He was [unclear phrase
involving tobacco/snuff], so they named
him Tabak.
Is it a great-grandfather?
Abe: Probably a great-grandfather.
Harry: I once looked up in a name of
Jewish names
Harry: and discovered a rabbi, T-A-B-A-K,
in Hungary in the early 19th century.
Sylvia: That's no relative.
Sylvia: I'm sure it's no relative.
Sylvia: I don't think we have rabbis in
the family.
Harry: But I suspect the name is older
than Pop thinks it is.
Frances (Fran): It probably is because
lately I've met a lot of tabaks.
See, my father's brothers, they
disappeared.
[Check audio] You know, Europe at that
time was no riding and everything.
[Check audio] So even a hundred miles in a
different star, nobody knew.
[Check audio] Really, where they were.
[Check audio] And it could be all the
[Tabaks?] that I'm coming across now.
[Check audio] My brother was in Russia.
They found the children.
[Check audio] The children.
[Check audio] Yeah, they found...
[Check audio] Still with that one.
[Check audio] Because it happened.
[Check audio] And one came in, a brother
and a sister, Kazamish,
[Check audio] with my brother's brother's
children.
[Check audio] So that's where they went.
They went into Russia.
[Check audio] They escaped in Russia. They
used to live in Helen, their estate.
Frances (Fran): Do you remember Rita with
her eating problems?
[Check audio] It wasn't that they had
these big, big, big problems.
That was me, Pop.
No, that was me.
I remember that one.
No, we did it more than once.
I remember the kitchen in the back.
You were there.
Frances (Fran): I used to spill the milk
down the sink.
[Check audio] Mike knows.
[Check audio] He lived in gardens.
[Check audio] Yeah.
[Check audio] How old is Ned?
[Check audio] He must be about three years
old.
Yeah.
So you weren't there.
It happened again.
It could have happened again.
It could have.
Oh my God.
[Check audio] He's dropping a piece.
[Check audio] He's just flying.
[Check audio] And he never did.
[Check audio] That's right.
Why'd he do that?
Why did you do that?
Well, maybe she didn't want to.
I don't remember, but I would have.
[Check audio] She probably felt
[deprived?].
[Check audio] [Unclear question or joke.]
Maybe it's just a genetic trait.
It's not just a genetic trait.
[Check audio] I take apples and I take
gum.
[Check audio] Don't we have an illustrious
trait?
[Check audio] A what?
[Check audio] [No reliable transcription
for this interval; check the recording.]
[Check audio] I have Abe's phone number,
but I don't know.
[Check audio] Carol and I sent away for
this.
[Check audio] I have Abe Greenberg's phone
number.
[Check audio] I went to America.
[Check audio] At that time she was about
39 years old.
[Check audio] I'm here.
[Check audio] Or are they 66?
[Check audio] She's about 100 already.
More than 100.
But we got the listing of all the Tabacs
in the world.
She was very nice to me.
United States, Canada, and Australia.
They love me.
And there are so many there.
I couldn't possibly go back as far as Pop
says.
[Check audio] The name had to have gone
back [more generations; exact wording
uncertain].
Oh, that's right, she must have been
watching me when Harry was born.
No, no.
Who watched when Harry was born?
You were a big girl.
So I didn't need to be watched.
I remember she took care of me once and
cut my hair.
[Check audio] When you were born.
[Check audio] Sylvia didn't remember.
[Check audio] She's like, why?
[Check audio] Now she didn't start to put
the lights out.
[Check audio] And I'm figuring out.
[Check audio] She's very patient.
[Check audio] She's saying, Ted, say Ted.
I'm trying to figure out what am I going
to do in this hospital?
Mama's there somewhere in this big
hospital.
How am I going to find what room she's in?
Oh, God.
[Check audio] [Six years old?]
Sylvia: I remember going out with him to
buy the stuff for Harry when Harry was
born.
Going to buy the crib.
I remember when he was growing up.
Smile again.
That was the first record. I thought you
bought that.
I bought it for him.
[Check audio] Frances (Fran): I remember
that [record player?].
Frances (Fran): I think you got the radio
and the record player came with it or
something.
Frances (Fran): And the record you brought
me, I don't know what happened to that
record.
Frances (Fran): Mama was so angry. Was she
angry? Oh God, did she give him?
Spend money without her permission?
[Check audio] I think she should give it
to him.
[Check audio] How old were you at night?
[Check audio] Frances (Fran): I think I
was like 19.
[Check audio] I got married.
Rita: And then I inherited the record
player.
Rita: The Strauss waltz. You bought the
Strauss waltz.
Rita: I threw it away, it was all broken.
[Check audio] Being with mom and I guess
you, [seeing Gene off?] when he was going
to the army.
I think it was, you know, it's a very
distorted image because it's an infant's
image.
Well, you're a little more than an infant,
but...
I used to babysit you.
I babysit her.
[Check audio] [No reliable transcription
for this interval; check the recording.]
[Check audio] I was made to sit here when
she had an awful reaction and almost
died.
[Check audio] What's the smallpox?
[Check audio] Is it smallpox?
[Check audio] Did I accept the last?
[Check audio] Did Peri have that?
[Check audio] No.
[Check audio] No, she called me.
[Check audio] She called me.
[Check audio] Bobbi: She said, [Harry?]
had that.
Sort of a boy.
Bobbi: No, it's not exactly a girl.
Right.
I didn't know what a sort is.
It's not exactly a girl.
Her father.
[Check audio] Because Grandma always
wanted [boys?].
and she probably had Harry.
Bobbi: And here I had, you know, girls,
and Harry had a boy.
So she wanted to break the news, but she
didn't want to hurt her feelings.
Bobbi: She was sort of a girl, but not
really.
Bobbi: It was sort of not a girl, but it
sounded like it was a...
Bobbi: Something or other.
Bobbi: And I really started getting
scared, you know, what's woman can say to
me?
What did you think of Gene when he was a
little boy?
Rita: Oh, Gene! What? I hated Gene.
Did you really?
[Check audio] Rita: Oh, God, he was so
mean. He [set fire to my hair].
[Check audio] Rita: He [set fire to my
hair].
How old was he?
Rita: He was old enough to know better,
around 16 or 17.
He was smoking.
With a cigarette?
Rita: He was playing around with it. You
know he's a tease. I was this little girl
and he held it up to my hair just to
threaten me and it actually caught.
Rita: You know and I could hear the singe,
you know, and it put it right out. But
it wasn't exactly the sort of thing that
endears one.
What did you think?
[Check audio] [Unclear words about first
impressions.]
[Check audio] So does I. For many years.
[Check audio] Yeah. So does I.
[Check audio] That's why he had to be
there.
[Check audio] I can hear it.
Was he a grump back then?
Oh, he was always a grump.
Oh, was he a grump?
He's not a grump back then.
He's a prude.
[Check audio] Oh, he’s [mellowed?].
[Check audio] He’s [mellowed?].
He's big-time mellow.
This is his hope for you, too.
Yeah, just don't.
We already started.
I've got one.
I've just finished telling that one.
I've heard stories.
[Check audio] Gene's washed your hair.
[Check audio] How did the audience feel?
[Check audio] He was teasing me.
[Check audio] Isn't it a match?
[Check audio] You know, it was a sweet
thing to do.
[Check audio] I heard he was torturing
you.
[Check audio] He never could stand there.
[Check audio] He was mutual.
You know, I can see it now.
He used to get terrible treatment from his
sister.
Oh, that's how you do it?
Rita: But I was his poor, helpless
six-year-old.
I know.
That's why he took the
The truth comes out. Where is she?
He's against women.
Not all of them. He's managed to save a
few.
He had a few. He saved a few.
[Check audio] Yeah, I better go get
dressed and play card games.
[Check audio] Go, go.
[Check audio] No, that's not good.
[Check audio] You look fun in the meeting,
don't you?
[Check audio] He gets along very well with
you.
[Check audio] Mom, but you're not going to
get married?
[Check audio] He's never with a man.
He saves it for sister-in-laws and wives.
And sisters.
Hey, Pop, can you tell me more?
Abe: When he was younger, he used to work
in a—you know, they used to make
whiskey.
Abe: So for lunch, he used to take a quart
of whiskey and a piece of bread.
[Check audio] And that was it for lunch.
[Check audio] My God.
Family member: For lunch, he would take a
quart of whiskey and bread?
Here it looks like we all have to get
changed.
How long did he work at that job?
Abe: I don't know how long.
Abe: Then he was working in a mill.
He had to gain calories somewhere.
How would you go back to work after that?
I don't know.
[Check audio] I don't know.
[Check audio] Did you have a child or a
grandchild?
[Check audio] One and a half.
[Check audio] So you must have been very
close.
[Check audio] So what happened?
[Check audio] I'm trying.
[Check audio] [Unclear conversation;
recognition repeated itself in this
interval.]
[Check audio] I don't know what he thought
of me.
[Check audio] He told me,
[Check audio] he forced up to see me.
[Check audio] He called me to meet the
[Check audio] Towers and I was there
[Check audio] with that.
[Check audio] All our babies were babies.
[Check audio] He was like,
[Check audio] Abe: he used to go away to
[Check audio] Abe: Russia,
[Check audio] Abe: the big town.
[Check audio] That time, I know
[Check audio] [Unclear words about
becoming a beggar.]
Abe: But nobody, he used to go away for a
half a year.
A half a year he's gone?
Abe: A half a year. He used to come back.
What's so funny?
Abe: He was saying, the money starts to
go, then Mama tells him, the time you
should go again.
Oh, so she sent him away to go?
Abe: She was the man, she was the boss.
She was the boss?
Abe: She was the business lady. She used
to have a pushcart. In the morning she
used to go pick berries. She was such a
fast picker. In no time she picked up a
lot of berries. And she’d run home to take
out her pushcart and go buy chickens.
She used to sell chickens and eggs.
Abe: In the summer, people get on vacation
in our town with a resort.
Abe: Rich people used to come and hire
houses by the peasants.
Abe: They just hired maids.
Abe: And they used to...
[Check audio] Depends what you guys want
to do, because you make a commitment.
[Check audio] The pine woods.
Family member: The pine woods were
healthy?
[Check audio] Pinewood, baby!
Abe: Even if somebody had TB… It didn’t
help them anyhow, but they went.
[Check audio] They thought you were
helping.
[Check audio] They were going to want it.
So they would buy the berries from her?
Buy berries?
Abe: She used to be the best cook.
Abe: She used to cook for weddings and bar
mitzvahs.
Abe: Even peasants.
[Check audio] She was such a [Yiddish term
unclear], you know.
Abe: She used to bake cakes.
Abe: The peasant made a wedding.
[Check audio] Abe: [They wanted?] Mama to
bake the cake.
Abe: She used to make all the decorations
and everything.
Abe: She used to make ice cream.
Abe: If she had time, she worked in a
bakery.
She was...
Boy, she must have been very busy.
So I can see she'd have no time for
anybody to just hang around and do
nothing.
What did your father do when he was away?
He used to...
Abe: In Europe, an old man, there was no
social security, there was no pension.
Abe: So he had to go out and beg if he was
poor. But he didn’t in the town that
knew him; he used to go away to Russia,
far away.
Abe: He used to go away for six months.
Abe: And then for the holidays he came out
there.
Abe: He used to go with another friend.
Abe: He had a friend, also a relative, to
a marriage.
Abe: He lost an arm.
Abe: So he used to go. He used to travel
with them.
[Check audio] Abe: [A man called Bezron?]
That man used to make a lot of money. He
used to bring home a lot of the money.
[Check audio] [Unclear overlapping
correction.]
Abe: My father, Friday night he used to go
to the shul. The rich people used to
take him home for the holidays. There were
other poor people; they picked my
father because he was a nice-looking,
clean man.
And every six months or so he would come
home for Passover?
For Passover.
So he didn't give up.
He would come home.
So your mother really supported the
family?
Abe: She supported the family. When Victor
got married, she went to the bank and
she made a loan.
[Check audio] [The tailors?] came in
[Check audio] our house
[Check audio] [No reliable transcription
for this interval; check the recording.]
How come she made it? I thought the wife's
family made the wedding.
Abe: They made the wedding. She made the
clothing.
Oh, the clothing and everything for the
wedding. That was what she made.
[Check audio] [Yiddish expression
unclear.]
Abe: She wasn’t educated, but she kept the
house. She was a smart woman.
It's the whole world.
Abe: In the summertime in our town,
[Check audio] The Polish people used to
make [unclear reference to church
celebrations or processions].
[Check audio] Used to bring [crosses?],
flags, you know, and Jesus.
Abe: And all Polish people used to come at
that time.
[Check audio] Four times in the summer.
Used to come the Cotorinas, you know, with
the music, with the parrots, with the
mice, to pick up the lucky number.
[Check audio] Abe: So my mother made ice
cream, lemonade, used to go out and sell
for the [peasants?].
[Check audio] [Unclear words about people
who came for vacation.]
[Check audio] They called them [word for
summer visitors unclear].
[Check audio] Abe: So she used to sell
chicken, spring chicken, egg, cheese.
What did she do?
Go out to the peasants and buy it?
Yeah, the peasants used to come and I told
you.
I bought it in the market.
She used to buy it.
[Check audio] She bought from the peasants
and then she [resold them?].
That's the mythology in the family.
She bought...
I'm sorry.
Yes.
[Check audio] We used to walk one time to
another.
[Check audio] We couldn't catch up.
Where is it?
In the back room.
I think so.
Are you in room 380?
Yes.
Wow.
Rosie.
Judy's the one.
[Check audio] [Unclear joking side
conversation.]
Rosie.
Fast, fast, fast.
Francis too.
You going to get ready to go eat now?
Abe: I'm also very fast.
Sylvia: Yeah, I know you are.
Sylvia: Schnell, Schnell.
Abe: I was working in a factory after I
retired.
Yeah.
Abe: I told them, part time.
Abe: Part time.
Abe: So they gave me $125 a week.
[Check audio] Abe: But I had to work eight
hours. And I had three hours [meaning
uncertain].
[Check audio] Abe: I did my work and I
went to go home early.
[Check audio] Why do you have to rush?